<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>SDN-Techtalk | Steven Schramm</title>
    <link>https://sdn-techtalk.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on SDN-Techtalk | Steven Schramm</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Steven Schramm</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2024 19:54:18 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://sdn-techtalk.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Antrea Egress - Controlling the egress IPs for K8s Pods within Tanzu</title>
      <link>https://sdn-techtalk.com/posts/antrea-egress/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2024 19:54:18 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sdn-techtalk.com/posts/antrea-egress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The integration of K8s platforms within a enterprise network environment is always a challenge regarding security and routing of certain K8s pods. Multiple pods are running in the same K8s cluster but might have different functinalities and requirements to access services outside of the K8s platform.&#xA;What should you do, if you are unable to assign a specific outgoing IP to a specific pod or group of pods? In this case you are forced to treat all the pods within a specific K8s cluster the same way and create firewall rules based on this.&#xA;That does mean all the different pods within a K8s cluster will have the same network permissions and it is very challenging to implement further isolation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ABOUT ME</title>
      <link>https://sdn-techtalk.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sdn-techtalk.com/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;me.png&#34; alt=&#34;Bild von mir&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;hi-im-steven---networking-and-cloud-enthusiast&#34;&gt;Hi, I’m Steven - Networking and Cloud enthusiast&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;and I’ve been navigating the exciting world of IT and networking since 2011. This blog is my space to share insights, technical challenges, and solutions that I test and explore hands-on in my very own homelab.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What started with a humble HP Microserver has grown into a robust environment, now hosting enterprise-level solutions like NSX and Tanzu. My homelab isn’t just a hobby—it’s a proving ground for cutting-edge technologies and a reflection of my passion for continuous learning.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
