<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Network on SDN-Techtalk | Steven Schramm</title>
    <link>https://sdn-techtalk.com/tags/network/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Network on SDN-Techtalk | Steven Schramm</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Steven Schramm</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 03:35:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://sdn-techtalk.com/tags/network/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>AVI NSX Cloud - Is it possible to preserve the client IP for traffic forwared by a One-Arm LoadBalancer?</title>
      <link>https://sdn-techtalk.com/posts/preserve-clientip/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 03:35:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sdn-techtalk.com/posts/preserve-clientip/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;LoadBalancing is a crucial feature to increase the availability and reduce the time to complete a failover for IT services. In the first moment it seems to be not to complex. You have multiple instances of your service and you forward the traffic to both of those instances to share the load.&#xA;But there a dozens of different applications and services with totally different requirements. Some of those applications are very simple and are dependent to local sessions or states inside a database. Other applications are stateless or the state is synced between the different instances.&#xA;Based on those requirements the following LoadBalancing features are a subset of the important features to understand.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving NSX Datacenter TEP performance and availability - Multi-TEP and TEP Group High Availability</title>
      <link>https://sdn-techtalk.com/posts/multitep-ha/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 12:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sdn-techtalk.com/posts/multitep-ha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some of you are using NSX for many years already and are aware of the different changes and improvements implemented in the last years.&#xA;I personally started with NSX in version 2.3 and one of the first important improvements I recognized is &amp;ldquo;MultiTEP&amp;rdquo; for edge nodes from type VM.  It was released with NSX 2.5 and officially added to the reference design guide.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By the way: The reference design guide is still a great resource to learn the design pricipals for NSX implementaions. This is especially interesting for those who might be new to NSX.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Antrea Egress - Controlling the egress IPs for K8s Pods within Tanzu</title>
      <link>https://sdn-techtalk.com/posts/antrea-egress/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Dec 2024 19:54:18 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://sdn-techtalk.com/posts/antrea-egress/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The integration of K8s platforms within a enterprise network environment is always a challenge regarding security and routing of certain K8s pods. Multiple pods are running in the same K8s cluster but might have different functinalities and requirements to access services outside of the K8s platform.&#xA;What should you do, if you are unable to assign a specific outgoing IP to a specific pod or group of pods? In this case you are forced to treat all the pods within a specific K8s cluster the same way and create firewall rules based on this.&#xA;That does mean all the different pods within a K8s cluster will have the same network permissions and it is very challenging to implement further isolation.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
